oh
okay let's do this
layers the boogeyman of all MTG judges
considered to be one of the most
difficult rulings in Magic's history to
understand but in today's video we're
going to be breaking down layers and
showing that they're not that hard to
learn once you know how to apply them
let's jump into it so what exactly are
layers and why should you care
effectively layers are the order in
which continuous effects apply
themselves to a game State whether
that's static abilities like honor of a
pure or until end of turn effects like
active treason or giant growth this is
similar to how we have bapnap to know
which order to resolve multiple
triggered abilities that occur at the
same time and depending on the order
layers are applied can cause some pretty
interesting interactions
before we go over layers let's start
with an example to think about
what happens to my non-basic lands when
there is a Magus of the Moon in play
which says non-basic lands are mountains
and the enchantment humility which says
All Creatures lose all abilities and
have base power and toughness 1-1
on the surface this looks pretty simple
and no doubt someone in the comments
will say oh reading the card explains
the card
but I can assure you it's not as simple
as it looks and I'll tell you right now
this interaction ends with all non-basic
Lands still being mountains confused
let's break down the layers
in Magic there are seven layers in layer
one we have copy effects like clone or
mirror weave in layer 2 there's control
changing effects like agent of treachery
or control Magic
in layer 3 we have text changing effects
like sleight of mind or something like
the overload mechanic
layer 4 covers type changing effects
like blood moon or Arcane adaptation
in layer 5 we have color changing
effects like Peter's servant in layer 6
we have effects that add or remove
abilities like humility or a chromos
memorial
and in the final layer layer 7 we have
power and or toughness changing effects
now there are a few different kinds and
they're applied in the following order
in layer 7A we have characteristic
defining abilities like those on
tamagoif or Lord of Extinction basically
any ability that determines the value of
a star on that creature's power or
toughness
in layer 7B we have effects that set
base power and toughness like insole
artifact or Witness Protection
in layer 7c we have effects encounters
that modify Power or toughness like
giant growth dead weight or plus one
plus one or negative one negative one
counters and finally in layer 7D we have
effects that switch power and toughness
like inside out or Twisted Image
now that we know what the layers are how
do we apply layers to permanence well
firstly you start with the original card
and its base Oracle text you then find
all the continuous effects that would be
applied to the card and then proceed to
apply them in order from top to bottom
of the layers list
the key thing to note here is as you're
going down the list once you apply a
layer it effectively gets locked in and
any subsequent layers won't affect them
now there are some cards like turn to
frog or Colossus Hammer that affect
multiple layers so it's important to
keep those in mind too
so let's go back to our Magus of the
Moon humility example
let's work out what layers are being
interacted with on magaz of the Moon it
says non-basic lands are mountains so
we're changing the non-basic land type
to Mountain so type changing effects
that's layer four on humility it says
All Creatures lose all abilities
adding removing abilities that's layer
six and it also says and have base power
and toughness 1-1
power and toughness changing effects
that specifically set the base power
that's layer 7B okay so now we've got
all of our layers worked out we applied
them to the game state in order from top
to bottom
first we head to layer 4 and change all
non-basic glands to mountains and lock
that in
we then head to layer 6 and remove all
abilities from creatures
but here's the catch because Magus of
the moon's effect has already been
applied removing its ability now doesn't
change the game State non-basic lands
will still be mountains
we then go to layer 7B and set All
Creatures power and toughness to 1 1.
this leaves us with a board state of all
non-basic lands being mountains All
Creatures having no abilities and their
base power and toughness set to one
so we now know how to apply layers but
there are two more things we need to
learn about before we become the master
of layers
dependencies and time stamps we need to
be aware of timestamps and dependencies
for when we have two effects trying to
apply from the same layer which order
would we apply them in
let's look at this example let's say we
have levitation and play creatures you
control have flying
and then our opponent plays Mystic
decree
what would happen here would our
creatures have flying or not
both cards affect layer 6. well this is
where we look at timestamps we apply
effects from the same layer in timestamp
order
timestamps effectively get put on
something whenever an object enters a
zone or a continuous effect is generated
by a spell or ability
and Aura equipment or fortification
receives a new time stamp each time it
becomes attached to a player or an
object and when a transforming permanent
transforms or converts let's take a look
at this classic example you may have
heard about this one before
what happens when we have humility and
opal Essence in play
to clarify humility makes all our
creatures one ones with no abilities and
opalescence makes each other enchantment
a creature with power and toughness
equal to its minor value
so what would be the power and toughness
of our humility
is it a one one or is it a four four
well that depends on the time stamps if
humility was in play first and then
opalescence was played
we would apply humility's effect first
setting everything to be a 1-1 and then
we would apply opalescence effect
setting all enchantments base power and
toughness to be equal to their minor
value
if opal Essence was in play before
humility we would apply opalescence
power setting ability first then
humilities making everything a 1-1
okay last and final step
dependencies most of the time when we
have effects occurring in the same layer
we apply them in timestamp order but
sometimes some effects outcomes are
dependent on the application of other
effects
beautifully if you have two effects
operating on the same layer and effect a
would change how effect B works you
could say effect B is dependent on
effect a
if a dependency exists you always apply
the dependent effect first
here's another classic example
what would happen when we have blood
moon and erborg in play in this case
because erborg is a non-basic land its
ability that changes everything into a
swamp solely depends on whether blood
Moon's mounting ability is applied first
that signals a dependency so in this
case blood moon would be applied first
which would remove erborg's ability
leaving all non-basic lands purely
mountains and lands would not become
swamps in addition to their other types
so to summarize when multiple continuous
effects happen we apply them from top to
bottom of the layers list locking them
in as we go and to work out the order of
effects happening on the same layer we
apply them in timestamp order or we
apply the effects that other effects may
depend on first
and there you have it you are now a
layers Master be sure to leave a like if
you learned something and I hope this
all made sense if you're still confused
pop a question in the comments section
down below and I'll do my best to answer
it
are there any other rules interactions
you would like explained let me know and
I may do a video on it thank you so much
for watching and I'll see you in the
next one
foreign